<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The best fee-simple, set forth in a sermon at St Peters in Cornhil, before the gentlemen and citizens born in the county of Nottingham, the 18. day of February, 1657. Being the day of their publique feast. By Marmaduke James, minister of Watton at Stone, in the county of Hertford.</title>
            <author>James, Marmaduke.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E955_2*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866655</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866655</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118933</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87498)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118933)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 142:E955[2*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The best fee-simple, set forth in a sermon at St Peters in Cornhil, before the gentlemen and citizens born in the county of Nottingham, the 18. day of February, 1657. Being the day of their publique feast. By Marmaduke James, minister of Watton at Stone, in the county of Hertford.</title>
                  <author>James, Marmaduke.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 33-59, [1]; [8], 1-24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.M. for J. Martin, J. Allestry, T. Dicas, and sold at their shop at the signe of the Bell, in St Paul's Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659. [i.e. 1658]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The everlasting Covenant" has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 29"; the 9 in imprint date has been crossed out and date altered to 1658.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118933:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>The Beſt Fee-Simple, Set forth in a Sermon at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> before the Gentlemen and Citizens Born in the County of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> the 18. day of <hi>February,</hi> 1657.</p>
                  <p>Being the Day of their Publique Feaſt.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Marmaduke James,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Watton</hi> at <hi>Stone,</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>MATTH. 13. 45, 46.</bibl> Again, The Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a Merchant man, ſeeking goodly Pearls, who when he had found one Pearl of great price, he went and ſold all that he had, and bought it.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>J. Martin, J. Alleſtry, T. Dicas,</hi> and ſold at their Shop at the Signe of the <hi>Bell,</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi>'s Churchyard, 1659.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118933:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118933:2"/>
                  <head>To the Right Honourable, And his Countries Worthy Patriot, HENRY, Lord Marquis of Dorcheſter, &amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will not injure your Lordſhips Temperance, in giving you a Surfet of the Feaſts of the Ancients; their kindes, Military, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and Sacred; upon Births, Marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Covenants, Travels, Inaugurations, nay,<note place="margin">Cutting of Teeth.</note> with ſome common (yet proper too) Feaſts at their firſt fleſh-breaking. The Scripture gave the Jews their <hi>Regalim:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Buxt. Syn.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:118933:3"/>And Primitive Chriſtians had their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gapae:</hi> And, through your Lordſhips quickning and encouraging influence, our Countrymen too, for theſe three years paſt, have been no Heteroclites from good Preſidents in their Yearly Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Copied out from our own, and other Nations.</p>
                  <p>Many actions that ſeem petite, are great in conſequence (as ſmal Stars have mighty influence.) This mingling, helps humility:<note place="margin">Cael. Rod. Antiq.</note> and uniting, ſymbols frugali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: this Traffique of hearts, amicabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: from theſe Aſſociations, men deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a reſpect one for another, as the Loadſtone and Needle do by contact: Thus Men (like Virginal-jacks) are ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together by the Teeth: and Bag-pipe like, commonly make beſt Muſick, when they are firſt blown full.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:118933:3"/>Yet all this is but a Herd at Paſture (for Beaſts can claw one another) till the Minde and Soul be conteſserate: For though ſome Seraphique Fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiques, would have the Soul, like the Philoſophers Sphere of Fire, to eat no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; yet this is found a popular Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as well as that of the <hi>Camelion:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr</hi> Brown.</note> for ſhe has a mouth, nay two for failing, placed indeed ſomwhat ſtrangely; one in the <hi>Ear,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Herodot.</note> the other in the <hi>Eye.</hi> To treat which came in that first Courſe at the Aegyptians Table,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>A</hi> dead mans Scull.</note> 
                     <hi>viz.</hi> A Head that ſpake without a Tongue.<note place="margin">Buxt. Syn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Joſ. <hi>contr.</hi> App.</note> The Jews <hi>Chidoth,</hi> as appears by <hi>Sampſons</hi> Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles (at his Feaſt:) Our Saviours Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables at his Swain Entertainments: Nay, our very Cheeſe-trenchers have got the parings of old ſentences on them, as if thereby they intended to Preach at
<pb facs="tcp:118933:4"/>Dinner. It was then very fitting at a Feaſt of Chriſtians, the Soul ſhould be careſſed, and firſt ſerved with her ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Viands; which was the true occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both theſe Sermons: the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation whereof (as additional to what is ſaid elſewhere) is no more, then by the Simpoſiaque Laws, as it were to paſs the Cenſor:<note place="margin">Pancirol.</note> and as Fronts and Porches are uſually ſet before Buildings, fairly Adorned with ſome Great <hi>Coloſs,</hi> or <hi>Gyant,</hi> Bowing under their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Weight; ſo are theſe Epiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary <hi>Praeludiums</hi> prefixed, which do no leſs Attaque commonly ſome Fair Name; with this difference only, That there the Houſe ſuſtains the <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſon</hi> that ſeems to pillar it, but here the Patron doth reallize the contrary.</p>
                  <p>And now <hi>my Lord,</hi> I am like the
<pb facs="tcp:118933:4"/>Sun in his Perigee, or ſlow Motion, at my hardeſt task: to account to your Lordſhip, why <hi>Conon,</hi> or his Rape, ſhould be a Perſon, or Preſent for the Court: How a Pilot, ſo obſcure for parts, and ſo little known for Perſon, can vouch ſo high a Name: Or that this Fraight, that conſiſts neither of the Gold of <hi>Ophir</hi> (to wit, any deep Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations) nor ſo much as the painted Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks of Eloquence, ſhould yet ſo boldly addreſs to an Engliſh <hi>Solomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this great ſtrait <hi>(my Lord)</hi> if the Queen Reaſon ſhould ſeem to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw her preſence for a while, I am ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the miſſion of her next Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, and principal Lady of Honour, I mean, <hi>Excuſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For grant it true, that the Comets on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhine for Emperours, and Princes;
<pb facs="tcp:118933:5"/>yet the Fixed Stars do influence the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed Peaſant as much as them; and and the meaneſt Swains are in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>qual Wardſhip with them, to the brighteſt Angels.<note place="margin">Gafferel.</note> Let the <hi>Taliſman</hi> Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors mourn over their loſt Art of attract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vertue of a Star, to Conſtellate a Vegitable therewith; yet we of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Orbs are comforted by what we ſee the Chymiſts do, <hi>viz.</hi> Extract the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Virtues better by courſe Dung, then by the Suns moſt Noble and Fiery Beams.</p>
                  <p>And certainly, <hi>Honour,</hi> the Jewel of the High can be Forged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nly (like Jewels) by the black hands of thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, in whom it ſeems more Fountainou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly to reſide, then in the perſons honoured; inſomuch,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. l. 1.</note> that the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eity it ſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all perfections, wanted this, till
<pb facs="tcp:118933:5"/>a Creation: As the Longitude of the Earth is taken by Eclipſes,<note place="margin">Carp. Geog.</note> juſt ſo (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) Your Orators obſcurity doth give aym to take the Dimenſions of Your Lordſhips Excellence.</p>
                  <p>Neither ſhould this ſeem ſtrange in him, though Cloyſtered up at home, and removed far from the practical know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of your Lordſhips actions, any more then the man immured from viſibility in his dark Optick Cell, is helped by that Blackneſs, through the little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unnel in his Window, to Landskip all thoſe float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Figures, and flying ſpecies,<note place="margin">Aquil. Opt.</note> that ſeem to loſe themſelves in the wandering Ayr.</p>
                  <p>And though <hi>(My Lord)</hi> Munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Bounty, with Learned and unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralleld Charity, concentring in a Perſon Nobly ſtreaming from Ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, ſets You up to ſhine in an high
<pb facs="tcp:118933:6"/>ſphere; Yet alas! the dire blaſts of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie often waſte thoſe Lights, Torching in a bluſtring Ayr, while blinde Vaults preſerve the burning Lamps for many Centuries:<note place="margin">Plin. Nat. Hiſt.</note> If ſuch effect ſhould from theſe papers happen, how much ſhould he rejoyce in that obſcurity that preſerves Your Glory? That, as a Corps wrapt up in Balm, and Spice, by the Retalia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting power of Your Name, will be kept ſweet, and whole, in deſpite of the teeth of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Envie:</hi> For, though the <hi>Tropicks</hi> and <hi>Poles</hi> move on their own little ones; yet in Menſuration, recourſe must be had to the greater Circles: So mens valuations paſſing by theſe Atomes of Work and Perſon, ſhall take the Riſe of their Judgments from the greatneſs of Your <hi>Noble Protection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet beſides theſe wide ſhoes, Laſted
<pb facs="tcp:118933:6"/>for many Feet, there are ſome more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for mine; I being a poor twig of that Corporation, that drew much ſap from the Roots; and ſo long joyed under the ſhades of Your Grandfather, of Dear Memory, and your late Departed (the <hi>Veſpatian</hi> of that Town and Country) Brothers Boughs;<note place="margin">Amor ac deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae humani generis. Suet. in vit. Tit. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſp.</note> both whoſe Fruits there (when other Families are conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Maw of Time) in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples choiſeſt affections will be preſerved. And now <hi>(My Lord)</hi> we Your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen look upon You as that Sun, into whoſe boſom their flames have ſhed their lights; as ſomtimes the expanded ſtreams of Brightneſs came in, and made a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwig of Glory for Heavens greateſt Luminary, on the fourth of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons day: of which we are daylie more aſsured, whilſt by Your great Humility
<pb facs="tcp:118933:7"/>(though an Eagle of the higheſt Ayr) yet You diſdain not to fly in the Train of the meaner Birds of your Country, to perch with them, and feed in their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vearies (their late Feaſts) and ſhew them an example of imping their large Plumes, in pious, and charitable exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, towards the feathering, and feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many other naked and hungry Birds of the ſame Covie. Among others, your Orator is in Arrears, as for your Attendance on, and Countenance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging his work; ſo for ſomthing hid in the bowels of the ſubject of both his Diſcourſes.</p>
                  <p>The firſt repreſented <hi>David,</hi> a great Man, putting himſelf into Gods Inns of Court, and there Profeſſing himſelf a Student of the <hi>Divine,</hi> as you in great Condiſcention have done of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:118933:7"/>Law. Thy Teſtimonies I have</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond ſhewed Jeſus Chriſt, that <hi>Lapis Theologicus</hi> (as the Scripture calls him) in whoſe queſt we never labour in vain; Deſtin'd by Heavens Colledge of Phiſitians to be Bruiſed, nay Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cind to Duſt, and burnt up in the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of his Fathers wrath; that ſo the World might boast at laſt of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Medicine, for all Patients what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. Thus have we ſeen Blood iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from one part of the Body, ſtopt by opening the Cock, and letting the Sluce fly from another Vein. <hi>It pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which Noble Science as in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the End crownin the Action, is not obſcure to the very Hoſpitallers, who pray that your Lordſhip may amply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb facs="tcp:118933:8"/>your Fees from Gods (not earthly, but) heavenly Angels: And if your Lordſhip (as 'tis not doubted but you do) to the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Phiſick,</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi> ſtudy of Gods <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> and <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> ſublime <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> you will without all peradventure be Entitled by poſterity, <hi>the Engliſh Triſmegiſtus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I am afraid, leſt dealing too long in <hi>Phiſick,</hi> I ſhould make your Lordſhip a <hi>Patient:</hi> If any thing in theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or this Epiſtle be ill reſented, as <hi>Luther</hi> was ſaid by ſome to call S. <hi>James</hi> Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Camp. dec. rat.</note> 
                     <hi>Epiſtola ſtraminea;</hi> well may be ſit down quietly then with a worſe character of his, that deſires to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred amongſt the faithfulleſt of them that honour your Lordſhips Virtues, and is in the work of the Goſpel,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Honours moſt humble and faithful Servant,</hi> Marmaduke James.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:118933:8"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right Honorable, and Beloved,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe ſhortneſs of the dayes, the coldneſs of the ſeaſon, and the remoteneſs of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ha's prevented, I ſuppoſe, the ſupplies intended for you; which ha's occaſioned my being here upon ſhort warning to ſerve you this day, as one out of due courſe, both beſides yours, and my own expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which I truſt will plead excuſe, if you have not a diſcourſe ſo well digeſted, as ſo honorable, and ſolemne an Aſſembly might ſeem to challenge.</p>
                  <p>Concerning our Countrey, much more cannot be preſumed as additional to what ha's been ſpoken in the two years paſt, without ſome injurie to the bounds of modeſty and truth, which by no meanes ought to be offered from the Pulpit: yet mee thinks it is not handſom, that ſuch a Solemnity as this is, ſhould paſs without ſome glance at leaſt upon the preſent occaſion, which in a particular or two, I ſhall (by Gods aſſiſtance, and your patience) diſpatch.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is, that not many years paſt, you heard from a learned Perſon, that in the Memorables of our Countrey, there was none found that had poſſeſt the chief Magiſtracy of this City: But now behold one in the Chair, that is not onely by his Office Gods Steward, and the Protectors, and this great Cities, but your Countries Steward alſo; an Honour that few Countries in <hi>England</hi> of late years have arrived to, <hi>viz.</hi> That a <hi>Steward</hi> has been their Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:118933:9"/>The next thing that I would commend to you is, two places of Scripture, which I ſeldom reade, but the freſh thoughts of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> and <hi>Nottingham</hi>-ſhire come in; both of them are in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> That of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, in the 144<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> the four laſt verſes, <hi>That our Sons may be as plants, our Daughters as corner-ſtones, our garners may be full, our ſheep bringing forth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands in our ſtreets, our oxen ſtrong to labour, and that there be no complaining in our ſtreets; happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe—yea, happy is the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> The other is ſpoken of the City, in the 48<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>Pſalm</hi> the three laſt verſes; <hi>Walk about Zion, tell the towres thereof, mark well her bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks, conſider her palaces, that you may tell it to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration following —for this God is our God for ever, and ever, &amp;c.</hi> In theſe two Scriptures you have a deſcription, and a correction; when <hi>David</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the proſperity of the Countrey in their Sons, Daughters, Sheep, Oxen, Plenty, Peace, hee begins to pronounce proſperity upon them; but as one that had forgot himſelf and left out the main, he corrects himſelf; yea rather, <hi>happy is the people whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> Juſt thus in the other Scripture, when he had deſcribed the ſcituation, beauty, and ſtrength of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> hee brings in the preſence of God one would think ſtrangely, and independently, as the complement, perfection, and <hi>ſummum totale</hi> of all that Cities happineſs; <hi>for this God is our God for ever, and ever.</hi> Truly, Gentlemen, this is the work that you and I have to do this day, <hi>viz.</hi> to look upon all the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118933:9"/>reported beauties and virtues of your Countrey, but as ſo many ſingle figures, till God the eternal Circle of Bleſſedneſs be added to them to make up the ſum: and therefore let it be our joint prayer, that God may be our God, &amp; our Countreys God for ever, &amp; ever.</p>
                  <p>It is no difficult matter to ſhew, that the oblige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God are as much upon you to be his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as ever they were upon <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> to tell you, (if time would give leave) that your Countrey doth match the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> in plenty, and pleaſures, and how farr that Town of <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> doth run parallel with <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> Was <hi>Hiera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> ſet upon precipitious hills, and is not <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſo? and as the mountains ſtood about <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> Pſal. 125. do they not ſo about <hi>Nottingham?</hi> and as there were two famous Aſcents in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> Mount <hi>Moriah,</hi> upon which the Temple ſtood, and Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> where ſtood that lofty Tower of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> incomparably perching over City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and is it nor ſo in <hi>Nottingham?</hi> where, upon one high rock, as upon another <hi>Moriah,</hi> ſtands that fair Church (if my rule fail not) ſome cubits bigger than the Temple; and upon another, yet higher mountain, (like that of <hi>Zion</hi>) ſtands that ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, over-topping Town and Countrey, the loweſt ſtone whereof (before it's diſmantling) was higher than the top ſtones of many others in the Land; whoſe climbing Towers, ſcituate upon thoſe perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular rocks, did aſcend to ſuch a ſtupendious height, like another <hi>Zion,</hi> as if the Spectators ſhould believe that they intended to peer into the clouds, or to pick
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118933:10"/>a quarrel with the Moon. Upon the higheſt part whereof, in the beginning of the paſt miſerable broyles, was the Standard Royal, of unhappy, and too late, (alas!) too late lamented Majeſty lifted up; which Caſtle, had not the diviſions been home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, might have ſaid unto all her Enemies, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Jebuſites, truſting to the ſtrength of <hi>Zion,</hi> jeeringly told <hi>David;</hi> That they would ſet up the lame and the blinde to keep that Tower againſt him. Further I could tell you, how that cryſtalline River <hi>Trent,</hi> like another <hi>Jordan,</hi> or that little River <hi>Line,</hi> like that Brook <hi>Kydron,</hi> trilling down by the foot, and as it were waſhing the toes of that <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> do ſport their ſtreams in the laps of thoſe Virgins meadows, whoſe beds (without a metaphor) are green, over whom this fair Town ſits as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Spectatreſs, ſmiling upon the ſcene, while the hills crowd upon her ſhoulders, as if over them they would ſteal a ſight of thoſe Valley delightfull pleaſures: and to conclude, like another <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> at what a diſtance does Shee preſent to the gazing traveller a ſtately and majeſtick Aſpect? upon whoſe fore-head, as upon a Jewiſh frontlet in Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal letters, ſeems to be written that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Walk about</hi> this <hi>Zion, mark well her bulwarks, conſider her palaces, that yee may tell it to the generation follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But why loſe wee time in ſpoiling the goodly face, and native beauty of that Town and Countrey, by the vain depictions of fooliſh Art? thoſe that are doubtfull of the truth of theſe things, have ſuch an
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118933:10"/>anſwer ready, as ſometimes incredulous <hi>Nathanael</hi> received from non-plus't <hi>Philip</hi> about the perſon of Chriſt in the firſt of <hi>John,</hi> Let them go and ſee. But here (Sirs) lies not our buſineſs, which is at this time to indeavour, that as God was in <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> ſo hee may be the God of our Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and their guide unto death. But (alas, Sirs!) as the ignorance of God in many parts of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, has formerly been too apparent, and much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented; So now in theſe dayes of light, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ſo call'd, 'tis ſad to hear of thoſe monſters in Religion, I mean the Seekers, Ranters, and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, how they have over-ſpred the beautifull face thereof. Juſt as the Sun, when hee diſplaies his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſpring beams upon Orchards, and Gardens, and thinking thereby to warm, and draw forth the fruits of the earth for the comfort of man: then do the ſnakes, adders, and ſuch poiſonfull creatures come forth of their holes, turning up their bellies, and beaking themſelves in the ſweet beams thereof; So hath this Vermin crept abroad in our Countrey, to the diſparagement of the light of the glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt ſhining on them: and though 'tis out of queſtion that the Divel, and the Jeſuite is at the bottom, yet many well meaning people, that both ſome of you, and I know, are led away with thoſe pernicious errors, who are to be pitied, and for whom wee ſhould have continual ſorrow in our hearts, <hi>for theſe our Kinſmen</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>according to the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſh, that have a zeal of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>but not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to knowledge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118933:11"/>I need not tell you that the ſoul of man is a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing, and the loſs thereof ſad in any Countrey: Yet mee thinks in the aguiſh parts of <hi>Kent,</hi> and <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> where I have ſeen ſometimes a whole Pariſh ſick together, the ſouls that miſcarry thence, ſeem but to go from Purgatory to Hell; But thoſe that periſh out of <hi>Nottingham</hi>-ſhire, go from Heaven to Hell; <hi>And Thou Capernaum that art exalted to heaven, ſhalt be cast down to hell;</hi> and as ſometimes when that mighty tyrant <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> fell, the nations floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked together,<note place="margin">Iſa. 14.10, 14.</note> and wondering ſaid, <hi>Is this the man that made the earth to tremble? that did ſhake King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes? Art thou alſo weak as wee? Art thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like one of us?</hi> So, when a ſoul miſcarries out of <hi>Nottingham</hi>-ſhire, mee thinks in melancholy Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, I ſee thoſe Infernal Spirits flocking about it, and ſaying, What art thou fallen from thine Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie? Art thou come from thoſe pleaſant moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to theſe Stygian Lakes? from that Lightſom, and ambitious Air to theſe darkſom Cells? <hi>Art thou alſo weak as wee? Art thou become like one of us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſerious conſideration of theſe things ha's put mee upon a plain practical Sermon, lately delivered to my people in the Countrey; which God grant may be preached more to your hearts, than eares; and that I may (though the unworthieſt of Gods Servants) be as a guide this day to lead you from your earthly, to that <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> that is above; and from your pleaſant <hi>Ur</hi> of the <hi>Chaldees</hi> to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to that Countrey, and thoſe Cities
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118933:11"/>that have foundations, whoſe builder and maker is God, and whoſe rock is Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is life eternal</hi> (ſayes S. <hi>John</hi>) <hi>to know thee the onely true God, and him whom thou haſt ſent;</hi> and therefore have I taken a Text which holds out to you the knowledge, both of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son, and that in the moſt excellent, and ſaving act, that ever was done for the children of men.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ISAIAH 53.10.</hi>
                     </bibl> Yet it pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him, hee hath put him to grief; when thou ſhalt make his ſoul an offering for ſin, hee ſhall ſee his ſeed, hee ſhall prolong his dayes, and the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand.</q>
                  <p>THeſe words do contain that eternal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which was made between God the Father, and the Son, for the redemption of mankinde, wherein you have the Work, and the Wages.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118933:12"/>The work, or what Chriſt was to do, or rather ſuffer, was death, <hi>When hee ſhall lay down his ſoul an offering for ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The wages is laid down in the latter part of the verſe, in theſe three particulars: Firſt, <hi>hee ſhall ſee his Seed;</hi> Secondly, <hi>Hee ſhall prolong his dayes;</hi> Thirdly, <hi>The pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand.</hi> Theſe two I ſhall open a little to you, and firſt of the firſt.</p>
                  <p>Wee reade in the verſe before the Text, it is ſaid, that <hi>hee had done no violence, neither was there deceit in his mouth, yet it pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him.</hi> This was ſtrange, yet, that a juſt, and a righteous God ſhould greatly delight (for ſo the word ſignifies) to bruiſe an innocent perſon.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> All that I can ſay to it is, that the heart of God was ſo ſet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mankinde to ſave it, that it became unto him a very pleaſant thing to limit his own Son in order to that ſalvation. But leſt that God, while hee is thus mercifull unto man, ſhould ſeem cruel to his Son, there are two things in the text, which clear up the juſtice of God. The firſt is, that it was done with his own conſent; and therefore it is read by ſome Tranſlations, <hi>Si poſuerit animam pro peccato. If hee will lay down his ſoul an offering for ſin. Et volenti non fit injuria.</hi> Secondly, that hee ſhould not be without ſome remuneration for this work; <hi>for hee ſhall ſee his ſeed, prolong his dayes, and the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If hee will lay down his ſoul, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118933:12"/>May ſome man ſay, was it a queſtion? did God the Father, or did the Prophet that writ this, doubt of this thing? No, beloved, but it is uſuall to expreſs the great Acts of Chriſt the Mediatour by an <hi>If,</hi> thus ſpeaking of his death ſayes he, <hi>If I be lifted up I ſhall draw all men after me.</hi> Of his aſcenſion,<note place="margin">Jo. 12.32.</note> 
                     <hi>If I go, it is to prepare a place for you.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jo. 14.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Non contingentium eventus, ſed conditionem pacti certis ſimè implendi ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat,</hi> ſayes one very well: which manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion doth not ſignifie the contingency of the event, but points out the nature of a covenant. Thus much of the firſt. The next thing which is the wages promiſed, is in three things; firſt; <hi>he ſhall ſee his ſeed:</hi> which is a Metaphor drawn from plants, which being ripe, do ſcatter their ſeed for the propagation of their kind; thus from one grain of wheat ſown, doth ariſe up a whole eare, which being ſown again thence ariſes many more, till a whole barne is filled with the increaſe of one corn. Chriſt was that grain of wheat caſt into the ground, and dying, hath brought forth a plentifull crop of Chriſtians; this expreſſion therefore doth import the plenty of the Chriſtian Church. Now the Analogy holds in theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, as one corne brings forth many; ſo from one Chriſt hath ſprung up many Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as the ſeed that comes up is ſpecifically the ſame with that that was ſown, and is ſo like it, both without and within, that it cannot be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from it; ſo are Chriſtians like unto Chriſt without, and are therefore ſaid to be conformed to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118933:13"/>his Image, within, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Little Children of whom I travel in birth, till Chriſt be formed in you?</hi> Thirdly, as the ſeed ſown, though it be pure ſeed, there ariſes up with it many weeds, as Poppy, May-weed, Tinetare, Cattailes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which on the one hand either ſtarve, or on the other burn up the ſeed. So in the Church of Chriſt are there many weeds of prophane Perſons, on the one hand, and Hereticks on the other, which much injure the Church; for where God hath his Church, the Devill will have his Chappel: <hi>Maſter</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>didst thou not ſow good ſeed in thy Feild?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 13.27.</note> 
                     <hi>whence then are the tares?</hi> Why ſayes he, <hi>the evil one hath done it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Though the Seed be ſown pure Seed, cleared and winnowed, or ſcreened from all chaffe, and rubbiſh; yet it grows up with ſtalk, eare, ſpire, and, blade mufled as it were about with chaffe; So though Chriſt was a pure Corn, yet that Seed, thoſe Chriſtians that ſpring from him, grow up with ſtalk, ſpire, and blade; that is, with ſinfull corruptions, blades indeed that war againſt the ſoule, which is invelloped and ſet round about with infirmities.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> Not to be too Poſtillous.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Seed is of a perpetuating nature; As we ſee from the creation of the World to this day, there is nothing of thoſe vegitables loſt, which God created at firſt; becauſe every thing hath a Seed, a ſtring, or ſhadow, whereby it doth propagate its kind. So is it with the Seed of Chriſt, which never did, not never ſhall fail totally, from the beginning of the World to the end thereof; <hi>and though the Archers
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118933:13"/>have ſhot at this</hi> Joſeph, <hi>and ſorely wounded him, yet hath his bowe abode in ſtrength,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 49.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3.</note> and thus, <hi>Sanguis Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum eſt Semen Eccleſiae;</hi> the blood of the Martyrs hath been the Seed of the Church.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>He ſhall prolong his dayes.</hi> Some men may ſay, how is that poſſible that he that was Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall with his Father ſhould have his dayes prolong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? This phraſe therefore is ſpoken to Chriſt as Mediatour,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 9.6.</note> alluding to the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> under the Jewiſh Pedagogy, which worſhipped God under divers Shadows, Ceremonies, and carnal Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for a time; Now ſaith God, if thou wilt dye,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.10.</note> thou ſhalt pur an end to thoſe ſhadows, and ſhalt have a people to worſhip thee in Spirit, and in truth to the end of the World, and from thence to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Burnt offerings and ſacrifice thou wouldſt not have, but a body thou haſt prepared me.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 40.6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>The pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand:</hi> Which is, the work of mans redemption ſhall certainly be accompliſhed; the ſame thing for which it is ſaid, <hi>It pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him,</hi> &amp;c. This is that which is meant by that which Chriſt almoſt every where expreſſeth; He was come to do not his own will, but the will, and pleaſure of his Father: And hence it is that he ſaid, He had not loſt one that his Father had given him, but the Son of Perdition. And thoſe laſt words of his, when he gave up the Ghoſt, <hi>Conſummatum eſt,</hi> it is finiſhed, 'tis done,<note place="margin">Jo. 17.12.</note> 'tis done.</p>
                  <p>Theſe words thus opened, you ſee the higheſt Mercy, and the higheſt Juſtice kiſſing each other;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118933:14"/>Juſtice, in that man having finned, man muſt ſuffer, though it be the Son of God;<note place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> 
                     <hi>That he might be juſt, and the juſtifier of him that believes in Jeſus:</hi> Mercy every word in the Text is big withall, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thy mercy is over all thy works:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.9.</note> even as oyle that being put into milk, or wine, or water, ſwims at the top, ſo mercy ſeems here to have got above juſtice, triumphing over it.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>It pleaſed the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. It ſeems then there was no neceſſity in God to ſave man, only it was his pleaſure, ſo that the redemption of man is reſolved into the ſame accompt that his creation was;<note place="margin">Rev. 4.11.</note> 
                     <hi>for thy pleaſure they are, and they were created.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>It pleaſed the Lord.</hi> It ſeems then there was no previſed merit in man; nothing in man to attract the affections of a God to him, only <hi>it pleaſed the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>to bruiſe;</hi> not by one blow to cruſh him, as Corn under the milſtone, but by a gradual death, to bruiſe, or pound him as Corn in a morter, as a man of ſorrows, to be worne away by degrees; by a living death, or a dying life; for ſo it is rendred, <hi>Conterere eum in infirmitate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>Him,</hi> viz. that was the Son of God. God has many Sons; ſome by creation, as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; ſome by adoption, as the Saints; but he hath but one Son by generation, and this was he; ſo, <hi>God ſo loved the World,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jo. 3.16.</note> 
                     <hi>that he gave his only begotten Son, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fiftly, <hi>His ſoul.</hi> Not only his body, but his ſoul; the greateſt part of mans ſin lay in his ſoul; and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118933:14"/>therefore his greateſt ſufferings were in his ſoul: or elſe what meant thoſe <hi>Grumi,</hi> thoſe great drops of blood? Why elſe ſo troubled? ſo heavy unto death? many Martyrs that have not had the thouſand part of his ſtrength, have gone to the place of execution, as to the bride chamber, kiſſing the chain, and ſtake, and hugging death (as it were) about the neck with joy; becauſe their ſufferings were only in the body, when their ſouls were comforted: the ſoul of Chriſts ſufferings was in his ſoul.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, <hi>For ſin.</hi> Firſt, that he knew not. Secondly, that he hated. Thirdly, for ſin in the indefinite, that is, all ſin, none excepted. Hence it is that he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Winebibber, a friend of Publicans, a Traitor, a Conjurer, one that dealt with Divels; 'Tis true, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly by man, but juſtly by God; becauſe he had taken the ſins of ſuch miſcreants upon him: <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> had ſeven Divels, and yet ſaved by Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, If you look upon all thoſe promiſes which the Father made to his Son, <hi>(viz.) He ſhall ſee his ſeed, prolong his dayes, and the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand.</hi> Theſe I ſay deeply looked into, prove more redundant to the advantage of the Church, then of Chriſt himſelf; as if the Deity could look beſides it ſelf as the higheſt end, and was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to make man the treaſury and the ſtore houſe of all his loves; which ſtupendious mercy the Angels are ſaid to ſtoop down (as the original bears it,<note place="margin">1 Per. 1.19.</note>) wiſhly to look into.</p>
                  <p>You ſee we have here a large Field; but my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is to point unto you only one plain propoſition,<note place="margin">Doct.</note>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:118933:15"/>which you hear of every day <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath laid down his ſoul an offring for the ſin of man, or Chriſt died for the ſins of his people.</p>
                  <p>That he died; is plain, or elſe, why did the Earth tremble? and why did the Sun hide his face, as if he was aſhamed to ſee what was done to the God of Nature? and why did the graves open, and the bodies of the dead ariſe, and walke up and down the holy City?</p>
                  <p>That he died for ſin, is as plain; for there is no death without ſin:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> 
                     <hi>The wages of ſin is death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That he died for the ſins of man, is ſtill as plain; for he had no ſin of his own: 'tis confeſt on all hands, <hi>that he had done no violence, neither was there deceit in his mouth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eſay. 53.9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>That he died as an offering for ſin, is moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: I might give you an hundred Scriptures; but ſhall one for all; <hi>And walk in love as Chriſt hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.2.</note> 
                     <hi>and hath given himſelf an offering, a ſweet ſmelling Savour.</hi> As if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, before Chriſt died, all the World ſtunk in the noſtrils of God; ſuch ſtinking, and poyſon us vapours did the ſin of man ſend up to Heaven: but after Chriſt died, then was the Scene changed; the World began then to ſmell like the Spring of the year, of Hony-Suckles, and Violets, and Roſes: <hi>He gave himſelf an effering, a ſweet ſmelling Savour:</hi> And indeed he was the ſubſtance of all thoſe typical offerings, and Sacrifices, which were from the beginning of the World; for they were either of things without life,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118933:15"/>or things that had life; he anſwereth them all.</p>
                  <p>Things inanimate were either dry, or moiſt; if dry, as the ſhew bread, then it was broken in pieces (for an offering was ever the deſtruction of the thing offered) Thus Chriſt was broken; <hi>It pleaſed the Lord to bruiſe him,</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>This is my body that was broken for you:</hi> Things moiſt, thoſe were either wine,<note place="margin">Mar. 26.26.</note> or oyle, and they were poured out before the Lord; thus it is ſaid, that <hi>he poured out his ſoul unto death.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 12.53.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>If of things that had life, then was the heart bloud taken from them; <hi>for without ſhedding of blond, there was no Remiſſion:</hi> Thus was Chriſt ſaid to be <hi>a Lamb ſlain from the beginning of the World:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 9.22.</note> Hence it is that <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt upon the ſight of him ſaith,<note place="margin">Rev. 13.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold the Lamb of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jo. 1.29.</note> 
                     <hi>that taketh away the ſins of the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lamb of God; why not the Bullock, the Goat, or the Ram, or the Calf of God? ſeeing all theſe were Sacrificeable Creatures; not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as ſome would have it) a Lamb for innocency, though that be true; nor onely as others, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that typical anniverſary Lamb, the Paſcal Lamb; but becauſe the Lamb was the daily ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sacrifice of the Temple; every morning, and every evening through the year was there a Lamb Sacrificed at the Temple, as the ſtanding Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for all Iſrael. Thus much for the Doctrinal part, We come now to the application.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> If it be ſo, that Chriſt bath made his ſoul an Offering for ſin; then they do very ill that bring ſtrange Offerings to the Lord. What elſe do the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118933:16"/>Papiſts, when they tell us that a man may not onely merit for himſelf, but ſupererogate for others? and poor ignorant people amongſt our ſelves, who think to be ſaved by their good meaning, by their good thinking, and by their good ſerving of God, as they ſay; 'tis true, theſe are good things, and to be incouraged, but not truſted unto in point of juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>We are all,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 64.10.</note> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>as an unclean thing, and our righteouſneſſes as filthy rags:</hi> our beſt actions are rags, but pieces of that perfection the Law requires, there is no whole cloth in them, they fail in their quantity: again they are filthy rags, polluted with original ſin, and ſo fall ſhort in their quality, and alas! how are theſe things to be truſted to?</p>
                  <p>It was the Law when any brought his ſacrifice unto God,<note place="margin">Deu. 15.19, 21. verſ.</note> 
                     <hi>He was to bring the firſtling male of the flock, but if it were halt, or lame, or blind, or had any blemiſh,</hi> he was not to offer it unto the Lord. What do theſe men do that truſt to their own works, but bring the halt, and the lame, and the blinde, when there is a firſtling male in the flock, whoſe ſoul was made an offering for ſin?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Was Chriſt made an offering for ſin, ſurely then there is no ſmall comfort for humbled ſinners? Hath the Lord affected thee with the ſence of ſin? Chriſtian look up to this offering!</p>
                  <p>It is with a man in the ſtate of ſin, as with one looking through a Proſpective Glaſs, while he looks at the wrong end, things that are great, and nigh, ſeem little, and afar off; but when he looks through
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118933:16"/>the right end, then things appear in their dimenſions at the very end of the Glaſs: Juſt thus it is while a man is in the ſtate of ſin; though his ſins be great, yet they ſeem little, and afar off is the danger;<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.5. verſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Thy Judgements, ſaith</hi> David, <hi>ſpeaking of the wicked, are far out of his ſight:</hi> even as the Stars, though they be bigger then the Earth, ſeem, but by reaſon of their diſtance, like the ſnuffe of a Candle. But when a man begins to turn unto God, then thoſe ſins that formerly he hath accompted little, begin to appear in their dimenſions, and affrightingly to ſtare him in the face. Well Chriſtian, hath God turned the right end of the Proſpective to thee? hath he awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened thy Conſcience? hath he written ſuch bitter things againſt thy ſoul, that thou now beginneſt to read the ſins of thy youth upon the Curtains of thy bed, and upon the windows of thy houſe? I mean, that every Circumſtance puts thee in mind of thy ſinnings againſt the Lord.</p>
                  <p>What doſt thou ſee? above, an angry God; below, a gaping Hell; on the one hand Conſcience, on the other Satan to accuſe thee? O direct thine eyes to this offering, to this lambe of God; that is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, and an onely begotten Son; ſlain for ſin in the indefinite; for all ſin, that thou maiſt receive com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from him.</p>
                  <p>Ah Sir, ſaith the ſoul, I am a great ſinner; you know not what a ſinner I have been, and of how ſcarlet a dye my ſinnes are. Why Chriſtian, if thy ſinnes be great, this offering is ſo. Sure I am, they can be but Infinite; this offering is ſo. Ah but ſaith the ſoul, if I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118933:17"/>had but a promiſe that God did in particular be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to me, I could believe this offering able to take away my ſinne: Why Chriſtian, thou haſt all the promiſes that <hi>Abraham, David,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and all thoſe bleſſed Creatures, are now ſet down in heaven by; thou haſt the ſame promiſes that Idolatrous <hi>Manaſſeh;</hi> perſecuting <hi>Saul,</hi> and dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> are carried to Heaven by. How particular wouldſt thou have the promiſes? <hi>This is my body which is broken for thee;</hi> what wouldſt thou have more? If thou doſt think Chriſt an hard-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saviour, yet thou doſt not think him a fool; Is it imaginable thinkeſt thou, that he ſhould be at all this coſt and ſmart to redeem a ſoul, and then refuſe it when it comes unto him?</p>
                  <p>To conclude, meditate upon theſe two Scriptures, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>He that comes unto me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</hi> John 17.37. <hi>In the laſt day, the great day of the feaſt, Jeſus ſtood and cryed, if any man thirſt, let him come unto me and drink.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mark how emphatical theſe words are; <hi>in the laſt day,</hi> As if they were the laſt words that Chriſt ſhould ſpeak; the laſt words of a dying man are hearty words. <hi>The great day of the feaſt;</hi> That is, of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, when the Tribes were met in Jeruſalem, when there was a whole Kingdom in one City, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus stood and cryed,</hi> at other times he uſed to ſit, and preach: But now he ſtood, and cryed; <hi>If any man thirſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 5.3.</note> 
                     <hi>let him come unto me and drink, &amp;c.</hi> If any man, though a great ſinner, be he Jew or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, Turk or Chriſtian; If he thirſt, without all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118933:17"/>without all limitation, <hi>Let him come unto me and drink.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> If Chriſts ſoul was poured out for ſinne, it teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us then with what eye to look upon ſinne. Many poor ignorant people when they read the ſtory of Chriſts paſsion, how angry are they at that Traytor <hi>Judas?</hi> that cruel <hi>Pilate?</hi> thoſe hard-hearted miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants, the Jews, for putting ſo innocent a perſon to death? Alas Chriſtian! it was not <hi>Judas,</hi> it was not <hi>Pontius Pilate;</hi> but it was thy ſin, and my ſin, that procured it. Sin was that which put upon his head a Crown of Thornes, that ſpat upon his bleſſed face; the Spear that pierced his ſide, Sin was the nailes that faſtned him to the Croſs; what remaines then, but that he that loves the Lord Jeſus ſhould hate I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity? <hi>Nevertheleſs,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>the foundation of God abideth</hi> ſure;<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.13.</note> let every <hi>one that nameth the name of Chriſt depart from iniquity.</hi> The like Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we have in the fifth of the <hi>Epheſians</hi> the 3 verſe, <hi>Let not fornication, uncleanneſs, &amp;c.</hi> be once named amongſt you, as becometh Saints. Let it not be done amongſt you, is good counſel may ſome men ſay; nay let not it be once named amongſt you, as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Saints. It is ſaid of <hi>Alexander,</hi> That he had a Coward in his Army, whoſe name was <hi>Alexander;</hi> ſending for him ſaid, What? art thou <hi>Alexander,</hi> and a Coward? either change thy name, or thy nature; either be not a Coward, or be not <hi>Alexander.</hi> What? a Chriſtian, and a Whoremaſter, a Drunkard, a profane Swearer, &amp;c? <hi>Non bene conveniunt nec in unâ ſede morantur;</hi> theſe things ſeem to be incompetible
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118933:18"/>in the ſame ſubject, and inconſiſtent with that love which a Chriſtian profeſſeth to bear unto this Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our that dyed for ſinne. If a woman having her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band murthered by an Aſſaſſinate, ſhould take that knife imbrued with the gore blood of her husbands heart, and kiſs it, and put it in her boſome, and ſay, this knife will I keep in my boſome all the dayes of my life; ſurely you would ſay this woman never lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her husband, was guilty of the blood of her husband; Thus the Apoſtle ſets forth the monſtrous nature of a wilful ſinner, <hi>Of how much ſorer puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaith he,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall he be worthy of, who hath troden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfoot the Son of God, hath counted the blood of the Covenant an unholy thing, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Heathens, ſuch as <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Cato,</hi> might by moral reaſons cauſe a ſtupefaction of their ſinnes; but the true mortification of ſinne ariſeth from the death of Chriſt; and certainly, no conſideration un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven doth more prevail with a gracious heart then this.</p>
                  <p>I have ſome where met with a ſtory of five Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who uſed to confer Notes about this point: ſayes the firſt, When I am tempted to ſin, I think of the ſhortneſs of life, and uncertainty of the time of death, and this makes me to live every day as if it were my laſt day.</p>
                  <p>This keeps me from ſinne, ſaith the ſecond, I think of the Anomy, Ataxy, that confuſion, darkneſſe, that is in ſinne, when I think of the great and glorious God, preſcribing a rule unto his Creatures, whoſe wil is nothing but reaſon for their good, giving them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118933:18"/>and well-being, that they might obſerve it: Now to ſee a man thus carried in Gods arms, to ſpit in his face, methinks it is ſuch an unthankful and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thing that I cannot but hate it.</p>
                  <p>But ſaith the third, when I am tempted to ſinne, I think of the day of Judgement, and methinks I hear that voice of the Archangel, with that Father, alwaies ſounding in mine ears, <hi>ſurgite, &amp; venite ad ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium,</hi> Ariſe ye dead and come to Judgment: and methinks I open the Caſements of Hell in my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, where I ſee <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Judas.</hi> and <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat, &amp;c.</hi> and all thoſe children of perdition, in thoſe bloody flames out of extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of torments, curſing the day of their birth, the God that made them, and the womb that bore them, and the breaſts that gave them ſuck, this makes me afraid to ſin againſt him.</p>
                  <p>Saith the fourth, I think of the Joyes of Heaven; methinks there I ſee meek <hi>Moſes,</hi> faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> patient <hi>Iob,</hi> &amp;c. and all thoſe children of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that by faith and obedience do now inherit the promiſes; And this doth wean my ſoul from ſin. Theſe are all good Conſiderations.</p>
                  <p>But ſaith the laſt, which is beſt of all: when I am tempted to ſinne, I go up to Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> and there methinks I ſee a ſweet Saviour hanging upon the Croſs, ſtretching out his Arms to Jew and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, as if he would graſp in all the world to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; There methinks I ſee his bloody temples, hands, ſide, and feet; There I ſee him ſweating, and ſighing, bleeding, and crying, and dying under the weight of my ſins: Oh ſaith he, this is ſuch heart-conquering
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118933:19"/>love, that I know not how to ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. This is that kindly repentance which God hath promiſed to his people;<note place="margin">Zach. 10.10. Hoſ. 14.8.</note> 
                     <hi>That they ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced, and mourn for him as an onely Son:</hi> When repenting <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſhall ſee this, he ſhall ſay, What have I to do any more with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols?</p>
                  <p>If Chriſt hath given himſelfe an offering for us, why then ſhould not we give up our ſelves an offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him?<note place="margin">4thly.</note> 
                     <hi>It is but reaſonable ſervice,</hi> ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, as reaſonable as an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> but alas! men are very delatory about this work. The Covetous perſon ſaith, Let him but obtain an Eſtate of ſo many thouſand pounds, then he will repent, and turn to Chriſt: The voluptuous, would reſerve one ſeven years longer to enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne; and then he will offer himſelfe to Chriſt. Moſt men defer this to old age, and death; but conſider with thy ſelfe Chriſtian, hath Chriſt made it his firſt work to dye for thee? and wilt thou make it thy laſt work to come to him? Hath he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven himſelf to death for thee? and wilt thou not give up thy ſelfe to life for him? Do but conſider the Advantages that thou wilt have by this Act: Many are the expreſſions in Scripture, which ſet forth the relation betwixt Chriſt and his Church: But there is none wherein the Spirit of God more delights, then that of marriage. Now there are three things (to name no more) which a woman that is well married receives from her husband.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, There is an exemption from all her Debts.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118933:19"/>If ſo be ſhe was five thouſand pounds in debt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and the Bayliffs come and arreſt her, ſhe tels them, that ſhe is not reſponſible, ſhe is now under Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Baron; and that <hi>lis feminae non intenditur,</hi> is a maxime in the Law. Thus a believer pleads againſt his ſins, when Satan, and Conſcience come to arreſt him; Its true ſaith he, I was Gods debtor, but now my condition is changed; truly I am not reſponſible, I am under the coverture of the Lord Jeſus: Go ſin, Go Devil to him that is my ſpiritual husband, to him that hath lead captivity captive, and that is now ſet down at the right hand of God; he will pay you every groat, or elſe he will ſhew you thoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittances that he took out for my ſin at his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. <hi>Bleſsed is the man</hi> (ſaith David,)<note place="margin">Pſalm. 32.1.</note> 
                     <hi>to whom the Lord imputes no ſin.</hi> He doth not ſay, to him that hath no ſin: for there is not ſuch a man in the World; but the man to whom the Lord imputes no ſin.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, A Wife partakes of all the honours, and riches of her husband: firſt the husband is the fountain of honour to the wife; if the husband be a King, ſhe is a Queen; a Marqueſs, ſhe is a Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; a Knight, ſhe is a Lady, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus what Chriſt is in point of honour, his people are. What was the native honour of Chriſt, but to be the Son of God? why ſo are they; Beloved ſaith th' Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.2.</note> 
                     <hi>We are now the Sons of God, though it doth not appear what we ſhall be,</hi> &amp;c. Though we be not glorified Sons, yet we are Sons as truly as he. What honour had Chriſt by Office? why he was a Prieſt, a Prophet, a King: ſo are they; <hi>Who hath waſht us in his blood,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 1.5.6.</note> 
                     <hi>and hath made us
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118933:20"/>Kings and Prieſts unto his Father,</hi> &amp;c. And that not in a metaphorical, but a real ſence, for every good man is a King; he hath got ſome victory over his corruptions, <hi>Et fortior eſt qui ſe, quam qui fortiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima vincit maenia,</hi> he is a ſtronger King that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quereth himſelf, then he that conquereth a City; and he is a Prieſt, he can pray unto God for himſelf, family, friends, neighbours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and God hears him.</p>
                  <p>Again, he is inſtated in all the riches of Chriſt; As where the husband hath a ſhilling, there the wife can ſay, is her ſix pence or groat for her benefit; the riches of Chriſt I have not time to open to you, temporal, ſpiritual, eternal. They would require a large diſcourſe; onely take one place of Scripture, which is the <hi>magna Charta</hi> of a Chriſtian;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.22.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Whether</hi> Paul, <hi>or</hi> Apollo, <hi>or</hi> Cephas, <hi>or the World, or life, or death, or things preſent, or things to come, all things are yours, and you are Chriſts, and Chriſts is Gods.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There was a difference amongſt the Corinthians about their Preachers, ſome was for <hi>Paul, Paul</hi> ſay they was a moſt excellent Preacher, that Preached in the evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit of God;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.4. Acts 18.24.</note> But ſayes another ſort we like <hi>Apollo</hi> beſt, for he is a Rhetorical man, and mighty in the Scriptures, and he worked the beſt upon our affections; but ſaith the third we are for <hi>Cephas,</hi> he is an excellent Caſuiſt, and he reſolves our doubts the beſt; Why ſaith the Apoſtle, will you like Children divide your own, they are but your Chaplains; Chaplains might the Corinthian, ſay, theſe are fit to be Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118933:20"/>to the greateſt Emperours in the World; why? ſaith he, the World is yours, <hi>whether</hi> Paul, <hi>or</hi> Apollo, <hi>or</hi> Cephas, <hi>or the World,</hi> &amp;c. but what good will the World do us (might the Corinthians ſay) if we cannot live to enjoy it? why (ſaith he) life is yours. But what good will the World do us when we come to dye? why (ſaith he) death is yours, that is for your advantage; but what will become of us after we are dead? All things to come (ſaith he) are yours: But might theſe Corinthians ſay, bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, ſhew us the writings and the conveyances of this eſtate; tell us, how we hold it, that we may not live upon fanſies, and build Caſtles in the aire: why ſayes he, you-hold <hi>in Capite,</hi> you hold of the Heir apparent of Heaven, and Earth; for you are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods: the Argumentation ſeems to run thus, you know Corinthians, that God hath all things; well, that's true; you know that Chriſt is Gods Son and Heir, and therefore he hath all things; well, that is true alſo; and you are Chriſts ſpouſe, and therefore for your good, you have all things.</p>
                  <p>The third, and laſt thing is, Thoſe Comforts that flow from their Union with Chriſt. As a woman that loves her Husband, receives more joy from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall fellowſhip and acquaintance with him, then from all his Eſtate beſides; ſo great are the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts that are received from Chriſt; which muſt needs be inexpreſſible, ſeeing the union from whence they flow is ſo great, that the moſt gracious and learned men in the world do not fully underſtand it in this life, which appears by that ſpeech of Chriſt to his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118933:21"/>people.<note place="margin">Matth. 25.34, 35.</note> 
                     <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my father, for I was an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and ye gave me meat; I was naked, and you cloathed me; I was ſick, and you viſited me. Then ſhall the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous anſwer, when did we ſee thee hungry, naked, or ſick, and viſited thee?</hi> As if they ſhould ſay, we confeſs Lord, that we have ſeen thy poor people hungry, naked, and ſick, and we relieved them; but did we do it to thee? to very thee? Yes, ſaith Chriſt, you did it to me, to very me; you have not yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the near relation that is betwixt them, and me; for in that you have viſited them, you viſited me, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>To conclude all, as the Love and Care of a friend or Father ſheweth it ſelfe moſt towards death, ſo we find the heart of Chriſt how it ſtood towards his people in that famous prayer before his death; <hi>That they all may be one,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 17.21, 22, 23.</note> 
                     <hi>as thou father art in me, and I in thee; and the glory which thou gaveſt me, I have given them, that they may be one even as we are one: I in them, and thou in me; that they may be made perfect in one: that the World may know, that thou haſt ſent me; and haſt loved them, as thou haſt loved me.</hi> See here what variety of expreſſions is uſed; thou in them, and I in them; and thou in me, and I in thee; backward, and forward; as if no one expreſſion was able to ſet forth this Union. Me think this is like the ſpeech of ſome young Heir, that having taken a wife againſt his fathers conſent, brings her in his hand to him, and ſaies, Sir, I confeſs this woman is below me in birth, breeding, portion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I have ſet my heart upon her, and have taken her for my wife, now good
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118933:21"/>Sir, as ever you hope to have comfort of your Son, that you will own her as your Daughter, elſe what good will my life do me? That the ſame lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diet, reſpect, attendance, may be given to her, that is given to me; and that ſhe may as truly in all reſpects be taken for your Daughter, as you have taken me for your Son; and that not privately onely, but that all the Servants of the Houſe, and all the Tenants may ſee, that you have loved her, as you have loved me; <hi>that all the World, ſaith Chriſt, may ſee that thou haſt loved them, as thou haſt loved me.</hi> I have done, the Lord give a bleſſing.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118933:22"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118933:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>The Everlaſting Covenant.</p>
                  <p>As it was Delivered in a Sermon at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Paul's,</hi> before the Gentlemen and Citizens of <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> 1658.</p>
                  <p>Being the Day of their Yearly Feaſt.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Marmaduke James,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Watton</hi> at <hi>Stone,</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 COR. 2.7.</hi>
                     </bibl> But we ſpeak the Wiſdom of God in a Myſterie; even the hidden Myſterie, which God ordained before the world unto <hi>our</hi> glory.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>J. Martin, J. Alleſtry, T. Dicas,</hi> and ſold at their Shop at the Signe of the <hi>Bell,</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi>'s Churchyard, 1659.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118933:23"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118933:23"/>
                  <head>To all my very much Honored Friends and Countrymen, the Reſpective NATIVES of the County of <hi>NOTTINGHAM.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>More eſpecially, To thoſe of the two late Solemn Meetings:</hi> And in particular, To the Right Honourable, Sir <hi>John Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Lord Mayor of the City of <hi>London;</hi> John Lewes <abbr>
                        <hi>Eſq</hi>
                     </abbr> and the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt of the worthy Stewards for the two laſt Feſtivals, held in the Years 1657. and 1658.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe firſt of theſe Sermons being Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied out the laſt Year for the Preſs, after ſerious peruſal, the Requeſt for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication
<pb facs="tcp:118933:24"/>ſeemed to flow rather from a good opinion of, then any real worth I found therein: and further, being diſcouraged by this fooliſh, and Voluminous Age, wherein every man almoſt (abounding in his own ſenſe) if the product of his thoughts amount but to the worth of an Egg, is reſtleſs till he cackles it to the Preſs; the abhorrency from which practiſe did make abortive that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
                  <p>Yet afterwards being wearied with the many Why-nots both of City, and Countrey Acquaintance; I almost repented the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted purpoſe; and beginning to reflect upon the Mode of the Times, found my ſelf in an errour, if the Directions of that Wiſe Man of <hi>France</hi> to his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar be true,<note place="margin">Charron.</note> to wit, <hi>That 'tis a great point of Wiſdom, moſt preciſely to obey the Cuſtoms of the place and age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:118933:24"/>we live, to prevent miſpriſion and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular diſdain, however irrational they may ſeem to us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And truly Gentlemen, if you could read that honour I bear You in my heart, You would eaſily believe your Entreaty to have the force of a Command upon me, though it were to much inconvenience: yet in the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance give me leave ingeniouſly to tell you, that I chuſe much more gladly to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the motion of the Preſs, then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the ſhock of another years Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories; and the rather, becauſe I have not found, either ſince the revival of your late Meetings, or in times before their adjourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by unhappy War, any thing extant from our Country of this nature<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which preſumes the Virtues, and Beauties thereof are not ordinary, in that that comly Dame, and keeper of the virtues, <hi>Modeſty</hi> I mean,
<pb facs="tcp:118933:25"/>hath hitherto been ſo ſtrangely prevalent.</p>
                  <p>For the last, my notice (through failed expectation) being ſmall, and ſecular diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions then upon me great, gave but one free day to recollect my ſelf: and I truſt a good interpretation will be admitted, in that this Goſpel-Text (ſeeing Neceſſity hath no Law) at that pinch was ready; otherwiſe a Text calculated for all the Countries un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven.</p>
                  <p>Plainly as it was Preached, you have it Printed, without any alteration, ſave only the particulars in the Analogie of the ſeed; which was then named, but the proſecution nipped off by the coldneſs of the ſeaſon: Wherein you have, as from the Father, the higheſt contrivance of heaven to be at peace with man: ſo from the Son, an example of eternal admiration, in the acts and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of his love to effectuate that Deſign
<pb facs="tcp:118933:25"/>for you. There ſeems to remain nothing more, but that you in a double ſence Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, after the exemplar of this love, may learn to love one another: and to the end that the great acts of this love, both of the Father, and the Son, may be ſealed to your ſouls by his holy Spirit, <hi>Let all bitterneſs, and wrath, and anger, and clamor, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſpeaking be put away from you, with all malice: and be ye kind one to another, tender hearted, forgiving one another; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as God for Chriſt ſake hath forgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en you.</hi> That ye may be united and carried together in the bonds and arms of that laſt-born,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.13.</note> but never dying Grace, to your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Country: where her twin-ſiſters, Faith, and Hope ſhall ceaſe, but that of Love abide for ever: Which is the hearty Prayer of him that is your moſt humble and faithful Servant and Countryman in the work of the Goſpel,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>M. I.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118933:26"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118933:26"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>PSALM 119.111.</bibl>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Thy Teſtimonies have I taken as an heritage for ever, for they are the rejoycing of my heart.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THis Pſalm is the moſt excellent Pſalm of <hi>David:</hi> excellent for the length of it, conſiſting of ſo many Octonaries, or parts, as there are letters in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Alphabet; excellent for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, all the parts of verſes thereof conſpiring with one conſent to ſet out the dignity of the Law of God; And indeed there ſeems to have been all divine frames upon <hi>Davids</hi> heart when he writ this Pſalm: Sometimes we find him in ſuch raptures, as if he was already ſet down in glory; ſometimes proſtrate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth in humble and penitential confeſſions of ſin, and deprecations againſt them; ſometimes wee finde him upon his legs, looking backward and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; forward, telling us what hee would do for time to come, <hi>Having ſworn, I will perform it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.106.</note> 
                     <hi>that I will keep thy righteous Judgments;</hi> backward, telling us what hee had done in times paſt, to which this verſe is to be referred, <hi>Thy Teſtimonies have I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe words contain <hi>Davids</hi> profeſſion of that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118933:27"/>high eſteem hee had of Gods teſtimonies, and the reaſon thereof; the profeſsion in the former part of the verſe, <hi>Thy teſtimonies have I taken as an heritage for ever;</hi> the reaſon in the latter part of the verſe, <hi>for they are the rejoycing of my heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt of theſe which is <hi>Davids</hi> profeſsion, my purpoſe is to open to you, as the doctrinal part; the other, in the application of our diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>The firſt which is <hi>Davids</hi> profeſsion, is one intire propoſition, in which wee have, as in every propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, theſe two things conſiderable: Firſt the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or matter treated of, which is in the word <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> ſet forth by their relation unto God, <hi>Thy Teſtimonies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond, is the predicate, or that which is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that ſubject, that is the word <hi>Heritage,</hi> ſet forth by its duration, <hi>An heritage for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And firſt of the firſt: This word <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> is that that is ſometimes called, <hi>The Word of the Lord, The Way of the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.9.</note> The Will of the Lord;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.10. Pſal. 119.1.</note> 
                     <hi>The Law of the Lord, The Commandements of the Lord;</hi> ſometimes, <hi>The Fear of the Lord, The Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.6. Pſal. 19.9.</note> 
                     <hi>The Judgments of the Lord;</hi> ſometimes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.8.</note> 
                     <hi>The Teſtimonies of the Lord.</hi> And it is obſervable,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.13.</note> that though there be an hundred three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ſixteen verſes in this Pſalm, yet there is not above two of them wherein one of theſe nine words is not named.</p>
                  <p>Some one may ſay,<note place="margin">Object.</note> What's the reaſon that <hi>David</hi> ſhould uſe ſo many words to expreſs one and the ſame thing? <hi>Frustrà fit per plura quod fieri poteſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118933:27"/>per pauciora,</hi> ſaith the Philoſopher.</p>
                  <p>Truly (Sirs) I know not what better anſwer to give,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> than that it is the property of Love to give ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Epithets to the object beloved: thus when Chriſt was in love with his Spouſe; <hi>Thou art,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> ſaith hee, <hi>my fair One, my Love, my Dove, my undefiled,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cant. 6.1, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible as an Army with banners.</hi> Thou art <hi>my fair One;</hi> I, but what if ſhee be fair, if ſhee be not chaſt? Thou art <hi>my undefiled;</hi> but what if ſhee be fair, and chaſt, if ſhee be a ſcold, a vexſome? I, but thou art <hi>my Dove,</hi> without all gall, without all bitterneſs; but what if ſhe be a Dove, if ſhe have never ſo much meekneſs, if that ariſe only from flegmacy and baſeneſs of temper, that ſhee is <hi>ſola ſocordia innocens;</hi> no, ſhee is full of ſpirit, life, and majeſty, <hi>ſhee is terrible as an Army with banners.</hi> Thus as Chriſt delights himſelf with various titles, to ſet forth the ſeveral excellencies of his Church, ſo it is with <hi>David;</hi> his heart is ſo in love with theſe Teſtimonies, that hee knowes not what to call them, Statutes, Lawes, Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Judgments, &amp;c. Sometimes when hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders of them, in regard of the Author, the great God, from whence they came; thus hee calls them, <hi>The Word of the Lord, The Way of the Lord, The Will of the Lord;</hi> when hee conſiders the divine ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty that they have over all Gods rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Angels and Men; thus hee calls them, <hi>The Law of the Lord, the Commandements of the Lord;</hi> when hee conſiders that great reſpect and reverence that a gracious heart yields unto them, thus hee calls them, <hi>The fear of the Lord;</hi> when hee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118933:28"/>conſiders their ſtability, and duration, as thoſe things which God hath ratified for ever; thus they are called, <hi>The Statutes of the Lord;</hi> when hee conſiders that great deciſion, and determination, that they ſhall make at the laſt day concerning the quick and the dead, thus hee calls them, <hi>The Judgments of the Lord;</hi> and laſt of all, conſidering that teſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that theſe make concerning God and man, as I ſhall ſhew you by and by, thus they are called, <hi>The Teſtimonies of the Lord; Thy Teſtimonies have I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is obſervable, that <hi>David</hi> delights more in this word than in any of the reſt, and by theſe Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies is meant the Word of God at large, but more ſtrictly the Moral Law, or the Law of the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. You know, when God gave the Law, he writ it upon two Tables of ſtone, and thoſe two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are called,<note place="margin">Exod. 31.18.</note> 
                     <hi>The Tables of the Teſtimony:</hi> Then God took thoſe Tables of ſtone, and put them into an Ark,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.22.</note> and that was called, <hi>The Ark of the Teſtimony;</hi> Then God took that Ark, and put that Ark into a Tabernacle,<note place="margin">Num. 1.50.</note> and that Tabernacle was called, <hi>The Tabernacle of the Teſtimony;</hi> ſo that this was ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous a Teſtimony, that it calls every thing Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that toucheth it, and gives a denomination to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that comes nigh unto it; and it may be well called a Teſtimony,</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe it was delivered with a Witneſs: when God came down upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod 20.29.</note> the mountain ſmoked, and the earth trembled, and there was great thundering, and lightening, and the ſound of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118933:28"/>trumpet, and hundred of thouſands of people that fled from it, ſaying, <hi>Let us not come near him, leſt wee die.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It may well be called the Teſtimonie; Becauſe as it teſtifies the perfection, and the holineſs of Gods will for ever, ſo alſo the Word of God witneſſeth the ſeveral Attributes of God unto the world; the book of <hi>Geneſis</hi> is a Teſtimony of Gods power, in making the world of nothing; his Juſtice, in drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world with water; his mercy, in ſaving <hi>Noah</hi> and his family, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The book of <hi>Exodus</hi> is a Teſtimony of that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſtupendious providence, that God exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over his Church, in bringing her out of <hi>Egypt</hi> through the red ſea, and that vaſt howling wilderneſs into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſo of the reſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It is called Teſtimony, in regard of that comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table or diſmal report it ſhall make for us, or againſt us, at the laſt day: <hi>Whoſoever ſhall not receive you,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mark 6.11.</note> 
                     <hi>nor hear my words, ſhake off the dust off your feet for a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt them:</hi> and thus have wee diſpatched the firſt thing propounded, What is meant by Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and why ſo called.</p>
                  <p>Wee now come to the ſecond, which is the predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, or what is ſaid of theſe Teſtimonies, that is, they are <hi>An heritage for ever;</hi> yet before wee come to that, wee may a little take notice of the copulation of theſe two together, in that word <hi>taken,</hi> which ſome read <hi>choſen,</hi> both the lections being emphatical enough to <hi>Davids</hi> purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>If the firſt, <hi>I have taken thy Teſtimonies,</hi> then
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118933:29"/>thus, as if <hi>David</hi> ſhould have ſaid, I perceive the Lord hath a minde to give theſe bleſſed Teſtimonies to his Church, the greateſt gift that ever hee ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, except it be the Meſſiah to come, and ſeeing that the Lord hath a heart to give, for my part I am reſolved to have a hand to take, <hi>I have taken thy Teſtimonies:</hi> or thus, <hi>I have choſen thy Teſtimonies;</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, The Lord hath laid before mee two excellent things: Here are my Crowns and Kingdoms on the one hand, and his Teſtimonies on the other; and if hee would put mee to my choice which I ſhould chuſe, and which refuſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably have I choſen his <hi>Teſtimonies as an heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An Inheritance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the higheſt expreſsion almoſt that <hi>David</hi> could uſe, to teſtifie his reſpect to theſe Teſtimonies; hee had been a long time lifting and heaving at an expreſsion, but did never hit it till now: In his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time (I ſuppoſe it was that) hee compares it to hony,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> and the hony-comb; <hi>Sweeter are they alſo than the honey and the hony-comb:</hi> hony is a fine thing, but money is better; money buy will hony, and ſugar, and a hundred things more; <hi>money anſwers all things;</hi> now <hi>David</hi> goes a little higher, and compares it to ſilver, but ſilver may be droſsie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.6.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeven times purified in the fire:</hi> I, but there is a finer thing than ſilver, and that is gold;<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.10.</note> why, faith hee, <hi>It is much more to be deſired than gold, yea than fine gold:</hi> I, but yet there is a finer thing than Gold, that is, Diamonds, Pearls, and Rubies, <hi>They are more precious than Rubies;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 3.15.</note> but yet ſuppoſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118933:29"/>a man hath ſilver, and gold, and rubies, yet hee may not have all riches; there are Cattel, Camels, Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Sheep, and Oxen, theſe were the ancient riches of the world,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.14.</note> 
                     <hi>I have rejoyced in the way of thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments above all riches.</hi> But yet there is one ſort of riches that is the ſweeteſt of all riches, that is ſpoil; when a ſouldier overcomes his enemy, and hath the pillage of the field, or falls into a Garriſon and takes the plunder thereof, this is of all riches the ſweeteſt; for here is a double luſt ſatisfied at once, not only Covetouſneſs, but Revenge,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.162.</note> 
                     <hi>Thy Word have I rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in more than in all ſpoil.</hi> But yet (Sirs) ſuppoſe a man hath ſilver, and gold, and pearls, and dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and all riches, and all ſpoil: Suppoſe a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man ſhould arrive to an eſtate of twenty, thirty, forty, fifty thouſand pound; Pray (Sir) ſaith hee, can you help mee to a purchaſe, I would fain have an Inheritance? Alas! theſe things may be taken from mee in a night, I would fain turn my perſonal into a real eſtate, have an Inheritance ſettled upon mee to deſcend to my poſterity after mee; now <hi>David</hi> is come to the heighth of what a mortal man could expreſs, <hi>Thy Teſtimonies have I taken as mine Inheritance for ever.</hi> An Inheritance then is that <hi>ſummum totale,</hi> that <hi>dimenſum,</hi> that lot, that portion, or proportion of eſtate a man enjoyes in this world, whether it be bequeathed by gift, or deſcend by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion, this wee call an Inheritance: now God, who hath given the world to the children of men as an Inheritance, hath reſerved a ſpecial ſpiritual portion for his people; in alluſion to which it is called, <hi>An
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118933:30"/>Inheritance,</hi> which is no leſs than heaven, and glory, and that it might be ſure to them, hee hath conveyed it all manner of wayes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Hee hath decreed it for them, <hi>In whom wee have obtained an inheritance being predestinated.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Hee hath bequeathed it to them by will. <hi>Fear not little Flock,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 12.32.</note> 
                     <hi>it is your Fathers will to give you a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It deſcends to them by ſucceſsion, and therefore they are ſaid to be born, and to be begotten to it; <hi>That hath begotten us to an inheritance incorruptible.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.4, 5.</note> Hence it is that all the children of God are ſaid to be the firſt-born; there is no yonger brothers in heaven, to every ſon hee alloweth the liberty and the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of primogeniture <hi>to the general Aſſembly and Church of the first-born.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 12.22.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>I,<note place="margin">Object.</note> but ſome will ſay, What is all this to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: wee know indeed that heaven is a glorious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; if <hi>David</hi> had ſaid, The kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven O Lord, the kingdom of thy Glory, I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for an inheritance, that might be eaſily under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, but that hee ſhould ſay, <hi>Thy Teſtimonies are my inheritance,</hi> that wee cannot underſtand?</p>
                  <p>It is true indeed,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> that heaven is the actual inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of Gods people, but it is as true, that the Word of God is their virtual inheritance; theſe teſtimonies are the deeds that convey this inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and how ordinary is it amongſt men to call ſuch the inheritance? If one of you come with a <hi>breviat</hi> to a Lawyer, and hee be diſſatisfied in any thing, Pray (Sir) ſaith hee. will you ſhow mee the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118933:30"/>inheritance, that is, the main deeds that leads to the inheritance: and we know that many times theſe old duſty moth-eaten papers are as much worth as a whole Country: Now an inheritance doth but theſe two things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> It diſcovers the eſtate, what quantity of acres, the butting and bounding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It doth convey, make over, and aſſure the ſaid Land to ſuch and ſuch a perſon, and to his Heirs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. Juſt thus doth the Word of God, it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers heaven and glory unto us; it is the terrier of the celeſtial Canaan, it holds out all that bliſs, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and glory that is treaſured up there for the children of bleſſedneſs, that exemption that is there from ſin, ſorrows, temptations, tribulations, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It conveys and aſſures all the eſtate unto them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch there was never any childe of God could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lay claim to God, Chriſt, to the Spirit, to Grace, to Glory, but by theſe Teſtimonies: Hence <hi>David</hi> knew what he ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.11.</note> 
                     <hi>Moreover by them is thy ſervant warned, and in keeping of them there is great reward:</hi> That reward is no leſs then Heaven it ſelf: Hence it is that the Word is ſo often called <hi>The Goſpel of the Kingdom:</hi> Yea, <hi>The Kingdom of heaven it ſelf: Repent,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 4.23.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 24.14.</note> 
                     <hi>for the Kingdom of heaven is at hand:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 4.17.</note> 
                     <hi>The Kingdom of God is come unto you.</hi> Hence <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 10.9.</note> when he bids farewel to the Miniſters of <hi>Miletus, I commend you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to God, and the Word of his grace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 20.32.</note> 
                     <hi>that is able to give you an inheritance amongſt them that are ſanctified; giving thanks unto God that hath made us
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118933:31"/>meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light:</hi> Not only in the light of glory, but in the light of grace, and of theſe Teſtimonies; <hi>For thy Law is a light unto my feet,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.105.</note> 
                     <hi>and a Eamp unto my paths.</hi> And thus have we done with the ſecond thing propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to wit, What is meant by this Inheritance, and in what ſenſe theſe Teſtimonies became <hi>David</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and ſo we come to the improvement of all by way of Application.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> If it be ſo, that the Word of the Lord is his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples inheritance, Then we ſee the reaſon of its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to this day, notwithſtanding all thoſe floods of malice that have been vomited out againſt it by Satan and his Inſtruments. What is the reaſon that the Aſſyrian and Perſian Monarchs, and thoſe bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Roman Emperours, that would have blotted out the name of this Book from under heaven, could never effect it? What is the reaſon that that Fox, the Pope, by all his ſubtilty could never deſtroy it: ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſetting the Church above it, ſomtimes corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting it with falſe gloſſes, ſomtimes obſcuring it from the people? What's the reaſon that thoſe Locuſts that are come out of the bottomleſs pit, I mean, the Seekers, and Ranters, and Quakers, who crying up a light within them, to deſtroy this glorious light without them, could never effectuate? Why you have the reaſon in the Text, It is an Inheritance: It is no eaſie matter to divide betwixt an Heir and his Inheritance: A young Heir may be under a Cloud, or a Sequeſtration for a time, but Inheritances will revert: God's entails are ſtronger then man's; and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118933:31"/>ſo long as God hath an Heir, a Childe upon earth, it is impoſſible to deſtroy this Book, this Inheritance: <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs away, before one jot,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 5.18.</note> 
                     <hi>one tittle ſhall paſs from it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> If it be ſo, That theſe Teſtimonies are ſuch an Inheritance, then that man that hath an Intereſt in them, hath little cauſe to be diſcontented in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. If thou beeſt a rich man, then bleſs the Lord that hath given thee both a portion in this life, and that which is to come: And if we have any Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man here that is a poor man, let him not ſay he is very poor, having an intereſt in that which <hi>David</hi> prizeth above all his Crowns; but let him ſay,<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto thy rest, O my Soul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> If it be ſo, That this Word of the Lord be ſuch an Inheritance, What is the reaſon that in theſe our days it is ſo ſlighted, and the love of many grows ſo cold towards it? We have a ſaying, That rich men never want Heirs: they may want children, but they never want heirs. Take the moſt mortified man, and him that is the moſt withdrawn from the pleaſures and profits of this life, if he hear of any Inheritance fallen, preſently he ſaddles his Horſe, and rides a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for poſſeſſion; for ſaith he, it is an Inheritance. If men did believe that this were ſuch, could they ſlight it as they do? When the Son of man comes, ſhall he finde faith in the earth? Truly Sirs, we have cauſe to think, that the laſt age of the world is upon us: I might ſtand here, and lament over the ſad Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy of theſe times, and might take up the expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118933:32"/>of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ierem. 2.5.</note> 
                     <hi>What iniquity have your Fathers found in me, that they are gone away from me?</hi> What evil (Chriſtian) haſt thou ever found in this Book, that thy ſoul ſhould loath it? What is the reaſon? Is it that of the Poet? <hi>Inopem me copia fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit:</hi> Hath plenty made thee poor? Or, Hath the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of this ſpiritual Manna given thee a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet? Or is it that of the Philoſopher, <hi>Nimis ſenſibile deſtruit ſenſum?</hi> Art thou blinde by looking upon the Sun? Or hath the glorious light of the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt put out mens eyes? Well Sirs, Let others do what they will, you that are my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, you that fear the Lord amongſt them, hold faſt this Book; for it is your life, and the length of your days; and when any one attempts to ſeduce you from it, ſay unto him, as <hi>Naboth</hi> did unto <hi>Ahab; Ahab</hi> was a King,<note place="margin">1 Kings 21.3.</note> and he proffered a valuable conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and it was but for a temporal inheritance, <hi>God forbid that I ſhould part with the Inheritance of my forefathers:</hi> Have all my Progenitors lived upon this eſtate, and ſhall I now debauch it? God forbid: There is <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and our Countryman <hi>Cranmer;</hi> and all theſe Patriarchal men, and thouſands more that are now ſate down in the Kingdom of Glory by vertue of this inheritance: God forbid that ever we ſhould part with the inheritance of our forefathers. And that I may faſten this Exhortation upon you, we ſhall a little open to you in the concluſion of our diſcourſe the famous example of <hi>David:</hi> It is to be conſidered
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118933:32"/>either firſt in the Practique, or ſecondly in the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory of it: The Practique is conſiderable, either firſt what the temporal eſtate that <hi>David</hi> had, was: Or ſecondly, what of theſe Teſtimonies <hi>David</hi> knew. For the firſt, I believe that <hi>David</hi> had the greateſt eſtate that ever mortal man had, except it was <hi>A dam</hi> in innocency: I know the ſtory of <hi>Darius, Alexander, Caeſar, Charlemaine,</hi> and thoſe great and mighty men upon the earth, yet, under favour, <hi>David</hi> ſeems to tranſcend them, if theſe three things be conſidered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                     <hi>David</hi> had a conſiderable bredth of ground over which he ruled; he ruled over <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> which was ſomtimes the ſeat of ſeven Kingdoms, over the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims,</hi> over <hi>Ammon, Moab, Amaleck; &amp;c.</hi> and if you compare 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. with the Hiſtory of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> you will find him to be Lord of the greateſt part of the Eaſtern world: But</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If you conſider the quality of his Subjects, which being good, is no ſmall addition to the glory of a Prince: <hi>What Nation</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>is there in all the world ſo great and ſo glorious as thy people Iſrael?</hi> There was but one people in all the world that was the Lord's people, and <hi>David</hi> was their King, and God's King: He was not <hi>Rex Diabolorum,</hi> as they ſay the King of <hi>England</hi> was; the King of Divels: Neither was he <hi>Rex Aſinorum,</hi> as they ſay the King of <hi>France</hi> is; the King of Aſſes: Neither was he <hi>Rex Hominum</hi> only, as they ſay the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is; the King of men: But he was <hi>Rex Sanctorum,</hi> the King of Saints, wherein he aſſumes the very Title of God,<note place="margin">Rev. 15.3.</note> 
                     <hi>O Thou King of Saints!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118933:33"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If we conſider the ſettlement of this eſtate upon <hi>David</hi> and his Poſterity; We think an eſtate ſurely ſetled, that is entailed upon the Crown; but alas, that Crown may fall in four or five hundred years, and then what becomes of that Entail? But <hi>David</hi>'s eſtate was by God's Oath entailed upon the Son, <hi>Once have I ſworn by my Holineſs unto David,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 89.36, 37.</note> 
                     <hi>that his Seed ſhall be as the Sun before me, and as the faithful witneſs in heaven.</hi> If you lay theſe things together, what an eſtate had <hi>David?</hi> Nay rather, what a heart had <hi>David</hi> to ſlight all theſe, for theſe Teſtimonies! We have not a drop to his bucket, to his Ocean, and yet alas, how do our ſmall eſtates draw our hearts from theſe Teſtimonies! Let us mourn over this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper. Again,</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If we conſider how ſmall a part of theſe Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies <hi>David</hi> had: <hi>David</hi> had but eight books of the Scripture; the five books of <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> and <hi>Ruth;</hi> this was all that <hi>David</hi> knew: <hi>David</hi> had the Law it is true, but he had none of the Goſpel, none of the Evangeliſts, or Apoſtolical Epiſtles: <hi>David</hi> had the Law, but he had not any of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators, none of thoſe Prophets called great or ſmall, lived in his time: I dare be bold to ſay, that that firſt Sermon of Chriſt in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. is worth more then all that <hi>David</hi> knew: <hi>David</hi> had the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that killeth; but you have the Spirit that giveth life: <hi>David</hi> ſaw through a Glaſs,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18.</note> darkly; but you with open face behold the glory of the Lord: <hi>David</hi> lived in the Dawning of the day; but you in thoſe times when the Sun is in the full Heavens, in its Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118933:33"/>O what would <hi>David</hi> have ſaid, if he had ſeen the things that we ſee! as Chriſt ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Many righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men have deſired to ſee the things that ye ſee, and have not ſeen them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Well Sir, if you lay the greatneſs of this eſtate with the littleneſs of <hi>David's</hi> knowledge concerning theſe teſtimonies together, for, <hi>ſic magna parvis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere ſolemus,</hi> you will finde him a famous example, and worthy your imitation: But if any one ſhould ſay, what is the reaſon, or what was there that <hi>David</hi> ſaw in theſe teſtimonies, to lead him to his choice from ſo great an eſtate? You have it in theſe words, <hi>For they are the rejoycing of my heart.</hi> And thus am I come to the ſecond particular, and the laſt thing, that is, the Theory in <hi>David's</hi> example; <hi>For they are the rejoycing of my heart;</hi> wherein you have three things inſinuated, Firſt ſaith hee, <hi>they are my Joy:</hi> Joy is that flower that groweth out of every good; and ſo far do we account any thing good, as it is joyfull to us; As if <hi>David</hi> ſhould ſay, I profeſs I have found more joy in theſe Teſtimonies, then ever I did in my Crowns and Kingdoms: It is a miſtake, when men think that a religious life is a ſad, melancholly, cynical life; It is true, the life of a Chriſtian is a life of temptation, affliction, a life of ſorrowing, and teares for ſin; and yet it is a joyful life: for we finde joy in our very ſorrows: <hi>As dying, and behold we live;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.9.10.</note> 
                     <hi>as ſorrowfull, yet alwayes rejoycing.</hi> The Apoſtle brings in ſorrow with a <hi>ſicut ſicut Dolentes;</hi> as ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful, as if our ſorrows were not reall ſorrows, as if they were but Analogical or ſimilitudinous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118933:34"/>ſorrows; But our joy real, <hi>verè ſemper gaudentes,</hi> alwayes rejoycing: and truly, if you look upon all the ſons of affliction in Scripture, you will finde they had their time of joy; poor <hi>Joſeph</hi> that was ſo innocently caſt into the dungeon, and thoſe heavy irons layed upon his young and tender legs, the text faith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.18.</note> 
                     <hi>the very irons went through his ſoule,</hi> yet he had his time of joy; and <hi>David,</hi> after hee was hunted by <hi>Saul,</hi> like a Partridge upon the Mountaines, had yet his time of joy; And <hi>Job,</hi> after Satan had diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all the arrowes of his wrath upon him, had his time of joy; And <hi>Paul,</hi> in the midſt of thoſe many deaths, hee was, <hi>as ſorrowfull, but alwayes rejoycing;</hi> men may think what they will, but the ſtate of a Chriſtian is a joyfull ſtate, for they are the joy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond thing obſervable is, the intention of the deepneſs of his joy, <hi>for they are the joy of my heart;</hi> As if <hi>David</hi> ſhould ſay, my Crown, and Kingdoms, Wives, and Children, they are the rejoycing of mine eyes, of my ſenſual and beſtial parts, but truly my rational and deep joyes, they are from thy Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, <hi>for they are the rejoycing of my heart.</hi> It is one thing to be merry <hi>ore tenus;</hi> this the men of the world have: it is another thing to be joyful; this only the Saints have; As the Poet ſpeaks of the river <hi>Nilus,</hi> that it is very deep, and the waters are very ſwift, and yet a by-ſtander would ſcarcely think they did move at all: The joyes of a good man are deep and ſwift joyes, and yet to others they are ſcarce ſeen to move; there was ſuch a difference in <hi>Davids</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts as there is betwixt the dew and the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118933:34"/>you know Sirs, that in a hot parching ſeaſon, if there comes-a coole night, and a fine dew upon the graſſe in the morning, it is a great refreſhing; but alas! when the Sun is up an hour or two, that dew is gone; but if there comes a ground-rain that laſteth for eight and forty or threeſcore hours, that reaches the root of the graſſe and trees, what a new face doth it put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Creature? The comforts that <hi>David</hi> had from <hi>Abſolom, Amnon, Tamar,</hi> and his temporal concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, were like the dew, for an hour or two, but then were ſcorched; but the joys hee had from theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, are like unto the ground-rain, that reached his heart root; <hi>for they are the joyes of my heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The laſt thing obſervable is, how <hi>David</hi> doth place all the ſprings of his comforts in theſe teſtimonies: For they, <hi>They are the rejoycings of my heart.</hi> As if a good man ſhould fetch all his comforts from theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: and certainely we forget our ſelves when we do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, and therefore it is that God doth uſually blaſt all the other objects of our joy; <hi>Son of man, I will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the delight of their eies;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 24.25.</note> 
                     <hi>their Sons and their Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi> and why? becauſe they were the delight of their eyes: <hi>Jonah</hi> greatly rejoyced under the Gourd, and the Gourd withered; God doth uſually diſappoint us in our comforts, that we might fetch them from his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies. We read that the Diſciples came to Chriſt, and told him what brave fellows they were: <hi>Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 10.17.</note> ſay they, <hi>the very Devils are ſubject unto us.</hi> Well ſaith Chriſt, Go on, tread upon Serpents, and Scorpions, and caſt out Devils; yet one thing let me tell you, do not rejoyce in theſe things: no, might they ſay, if ever mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal men had cauſe to rejoyce, we have: Have we not the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118933:35"/>power of God upon earth? the very Devils are ſubject unto us; No ſaith Chriſt, do not rejoyce in theſe things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> why, what then muſt we rejoyce in? that <hi>your names are written in Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I dare be bold to ſay, that no man ever yet entred into Heaven, whoſe name was not firſt written in this book; in the book of the Promiſes, in the book of Life; hence it is that you ſhall ſeldom read of theſe teſtimonies, but there is joy with them: if this word be preached, there is great joy;<note place="margin">Acts 8.8.</note> when <hi>Philip</hi> preached the word in <hi>Samaria, there was great joy in that City:</hi> if two Chriſtians do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer upon this word, there will be ſtrange motions of heart:<note place="margin">Luke 24.32.</note> 
                     <hi>Did not we feel our hearts burning within us, when hee ſpake unto us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a man (one of theſe long winter nights, when he cannot ſleep) doth but think of theſe Commandments, there is great joy; <hi>O how do I love thy Law, it is my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation day and night.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.91.</note> If a man doth but put forth his hand to execute one of theſe Commandments, there is great joy:<note place="margin">Prov. 21.15.</note> 
                     <hi>It is a joy to the juſt to do judgment,</hi> What joy have they that keep thy Commandments? And truly Sirs, there is one conveniency in theſe, above all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; that they ſtand by a man, when others fail him: If a man hath a beautiful wife, towardly children, a great eſtate, and if God throws this man into diſtreſs, they do but tumble upon him, like an old houſe upon his head, and then it's his miſery that he cannot be miſerable him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but he muſt make all his ſweet relations miſerable with him: but theſe Teſtimonies ſtand by a man in the ſaddeſt hours: This <hi>David</hi> well knew, when he made his choice, as appears by two verſes in this <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thy Statutes have been my Songs in the houſe of my Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.54.</note>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118933:35"/>Where was it that <hi>David</hi> was a Pilgrim? You know that <hi>David</hi> was a baniſhed King, he was hunted by <hi>Saul</hi> out of <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> fled to <hi>Achiſh,</hi> King of <hi>Gath,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 21.12.</note> poor man! lept out of the frying pan into the fire; at home he was purſued as a Traitor; abroad, was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended as a Spy; truly, it was a very fad condition: where was his ſupport now? Why, ſaith he, <hi>Thy ſtatutes have been my ſongs in the houſe of my Pilgrimage.</hi> The other is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I had then periſhed in my afflictions,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſe 92.</note> 
                     <hi>had not thy Law been my delight.</hi> I had then periſhed, when was that? Very probably at <hi>Ziklag: Ziklag</hi> was the greateſt diſtreſs that ever we read <hi>David</hi> was in; <hi>Ziklag</hi> was a Frontier Town belonging to the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and there they ſuffered <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to live;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 30.</note> the <hi>Amalakites</hi> came and take away all their ſtuff, children, wives, and concubines, bag, and baggage, burnt the City with fire, and the worſt was, that his own ſouldiers mutined againſt him; nothing would ſerve them, but the ſtoning of <hi>David:</hi> the Text ſaith, <hi>That he wept, till hee could weep no more:</hi> But at the laſt he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted himſelf in the Lord his God (poor man! little had he elſe to comfort himſelf in) that is, there was ſome Statute, ſome Judgment, ſome Teſtimony of the Lord that came into his minde at that time, that did comfort him: <hi>I had periſhed in my afflictions, had not thy Law been my delight.</hi> O happy is that man that hath an intereſt in theſe Teſtimonies, to comfort him in the ſaddeſt hour.</p>
                  <p>It is the uſual cuſtom at theſe Yearly Meetings, to ſpeak ſomwhat of the Country, the Soyl, Scituation, Antiquities Commodities, and Memorable Accidents thereof: How laudable this cuſtome is, I ſhall not here diſpute, but do purpoſe not to practiſe much of it at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118933:36"/>this time; for all them that are here preſent this day, are either of the Country, or ſtrangers: If the firſt, I can but tell them what by experience they better know; which ſeems to me, but as the carrying of coals to <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle;</hi> or the lighting of a candle to the Sun. If ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, they are prejudiced with the knowledge of that love every one bears to his Native Country, and they will think that we read them a Lecture more through the ſpectacles of Affection, then Judgement; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Memorables of our Country were ſo well reaped the laſt Year, that paſſing what was then deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the gleanings will ſcarce be a handful to preſent you withal; and <hi>repetita ſordent:</hi> You had then at large the Chronological and Geographical Deſcription of it,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>M.</hi> Fuller.</note> by him that is the <hi>Camden</hi> of our age for Antiquities, and our Engliſh <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> for Eloquence; neither is it conſiſtent with the modeſty of my Years and Parts, to attempt the poliſhing of that which he hath perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; or with my trembling hand, to draw a line after that <hi>Apelles:</hi> Let it be the practiſe of others at theſe their Anniverſary Meetings, to Paint over their dirty and ſickly Countries, and by ſcraping here and there a clean bit together, to flatter and befool their Country-Citizens, with the figmentitious Landskips of their Countries Beauties: Our Country needs no commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that's all commendation; her praiſes are in the Gates; and fearful I am to enter the Confines of Her, being conſcious to my ſelf to be more able to ſully and darken the Beauties thereof, then to expreſs them; yet that She may not be altogether paſſed over in ſilence, give me leave to tell you a ſtory of a Learned and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant Traveller, much redounding to the honour of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118933:36"/>our Country; and they ſay, ſomtimes a By-ſtander ſees more then the Gameſter.</p>
                  <p>Long ſince in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I was acquainted with a young Gentleman, whoſe addictions were to Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and Travels; whom after many years ſpent beyond Seas, it was my happineſs to meet with, ſoon after his receſs into <hi>England;</hi> and enquiring concerning ſome <hi>Italian</hi> Cities, and others of Fame in other Countries, which we much hear and read of; he affirmed, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificence and ſtately Buildings of ſome, the Riches and Trade of others, the pleaſant Scituation of others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſince my return, ſaid he, I have been in your Country of <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> and ſpent ſome time in the curious obſervation thereof; and do ſeriouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that for Delicacy of Scituation, and for all kinde of Conveniences reſpecting the life of Man, I never ſaw the like; and where, if the concernments of my Eſtate and Friends would admit, I could deſire to live and die in, above any Country that ever I yet ſaw in the European world.</p>
                  <p>A Country, in reſpect of the Sandy and Foreftical part, affording ſuch variety of pleaſures; of ſo dry, pleaſant, and healthful an Ayr, in reſpect of the other cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the clay, and its contiguity to the rich Vale <hi>Belvoir,</hi> all ſorts of grain and corn, in reſpect of that famous Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Trent,</hi> abounding with variety of Fiſh and Fowl, and the fertile Paſtures upon her banks, with all ſorts of fatted Cattel; a Country where the rates of all things carry that moderation, as not ſo low to be contemned, nor ſo high as to be refuſed; A Country, not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with wood for the Chamber, but that light and laſting culinary fire, the pit-coal; watred with the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118933:37"/>ſtreams of <hi>Trent,</hi> and other Rivers; bleſſed with ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Ayr, and richneſs of earth; as if all the Elements did conſpire to make her people happy.</p>
                  <p>In the Southweſt whereof, ſits the fair Town of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> delicately (like a Lady upon the Rocks) <hi>in collem ſub montibus,</hi> the beſt of all ſcituations, ſaith the Naturaliſt, her chair being flanked with the Hils, Eaſt, Weſt, and North, to keep off thoſe churliſh winds that might give her a cold in her Neck; her beautiful Face only diſplaid to the warm Southerly Sun, where ſhe beholds from on high the flowery Meadows, and the Trental ſtreams, with no ſmall delight; a Town ſcituate ſo near the River, that ſhe may have the conveniencies of Proſpect, Fiſh, and Navigation; and yet at ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as that ſhe is exempted from the crude, raw, and Aguiſh vapours thereof; the only inconveniences at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending ſuch ſweet Streams; over againſt whom, after that ſilver ſtreamed River <hi>Trent,</hi> hath with marvellous celerity poſted out of <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> begins here to halt, and demur upon her motion, and by various Meanders and twining circuitions, making one mile three, as if ſhe did greatly delight her ſelf in the views and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>views of that beautiful Country, and the Metropolis thereof: And thus we take our leave of that fair Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Town of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> which <hi>Drayton</hi> calls <hi>The Norths Imperial Eye,</hi> and which indeed (conſidering her lofty Elevation, from whence ſhe looks into all her Neighbouring Countries) may rather be compared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Wiſdom in <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. ſtretching forth her hands unto them, and ſaying, <hi>Come unto me all ye ſimple ones, and ye that lack underſtanding; for at my right hand is length of days, and upon my left hand, riches and honour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118933:37"/>It was a witty and a cloſe anſwer that was ſomtimes given by an accompliſh'd Prelate of this Land to a fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh King thereof; who upbraiding his height in Church and State, with the meaneſs of his deſcent, to wit, that his Father was a Taylor; made this reply, That if his Majeſty had exceeded his Father, as much as he had done his, he had bin the braveſt Prince in Chriſtendom. The Solution is this, That if our Countrymen did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed other Countrymen in their works of Piety and Charity, as far as our Country exceeds other Countries, you would be the braveſt men this day upon the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh earth: But alas! it is a ſad, an ancient obſervation of Divines, That thoſe Countries into whoſe boſom God hath poured the greateſt of theſe bleſſings, have been moſt unmindful of him.</p>
                  <p>Some think that God would have <hi>Abraham</hi> from <hi>Ur</hi> of the Caldees, as if the delicacy, pleaſures, temptations of that place, were inconſiſtent with that height of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that God would have the Fathers of the Faithful trained up unto; and certain I am, that <hi>Aàmah, Zeboim,</hi> &amp;c. and thoſe other famous infamous God-forgetting Cities, were upon a Plain, which was like unto the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice of God: I would not here be miſ-interpreted, as if I came to upbraid our Countrymen; it is an ill Bird that defiles her own Neſt; but out of love, <hi>in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem cantelam:</hi> for theſe things that are written, were written for an example to you in that delicate Country, that you might take heed: Though truly Sirs, let me be ſo far bold to tell you, It is a wonderment to ſome, to hear what other Countries have done at theſe their meetings, and nothing is extant from ours; neither is it to be doubted, but that there is as great a <hi>materia</hi> of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118933:38"/>goodneſs in you, as in any other of your Neighbors: Is there not ſome honourable perſon or perſons of our Country, the fame of whoſe Learning, Piety, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Actions of all kinds, is gone out through the Land? And for ought I know, the reſt of you in your inferiour Orbs are like minded; for generous Ayrs breed generous Diſpoſitions; but as Phiſitians ſay, That though blood be the life of the Body, yet the ſtrongeſt Conſtitutions do the ſooneſt periſh by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundancy thereof: So Gentlemen, if theſe Meetings be longer continued, and nothing done, the fears are, leſt that your Charity ſhould die of a Pluriſie, I mean, for want of evacuation.</p>
                  <p>If it ſhall here be demanded, What is that good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired? I dare not be ſo ſawcy as to preſcribe to your Wiſdoms; preſt I am much to ſpeak, and yet afraid to ſpeak: four and twenty miles have I come to ſerve you. this ſlabby weather; if I ſhould now offend you, how ſad would my return be home again? <hi>Extremo actu de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere turpiſſimum eſt:</hi> I ſhall only add one inſtance, and leave you to ſpell out the reſt: Are there not ſome of you of our Countrymen Citizens here? I know there are, to whom God hath given great Eſtates, and little or no Iſſue; that may as truly ſay (if they would ſpeak their Conſciences) of the River <hi>Trent,</hi> as ever <hi>Jacob</hi> did of <hi>Jordan:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cen. 32.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Over this Brook came I with this Staff, and behold the Lord hath made me two Bands. And Jacob aroſe, and built there an Altar unto the Lord.</hi> I have done, the Lord give a bleſſing.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
